# 别弄鱼上 让它四周围
Don’t pour the sauce over the fish, instead, spread it around the fish
# 古法蒸武昌鱼 武汉好久不见
Old School Steamed Wuchang Fish. Wuhan, long time no see
# 都什么食材啊
What ingredients do you have here?
# 你看看 黄花 木耳 红枣
Look, we have daylilies, black fungus, red dates
# 蒸的时候 必须加点肥膘
And some fatty pork to put on the fish when steaming
# 我们过去是加网油 现在咱没有了
We used to add caul fat, but now we don’t have that anymore
# 咱就使点肥肉片将就将就
So we just use the fatty pork as an alternative
# 你先铰着鱼
Trim the fish first
# 其实按理说 这还缺一道工序呢
To be honest, there should be another step here
# 得烫一下
We need to blanch the fish
# 今儿咱就不烫了
We are not blanching it today
# 修理修理就行了
We will just trim it
# 咱先给它改刀 先把鱼头给它拿掉
Let’s score the fish. Firstly, cut off its head
# 今天做的菜是老菜老味道的
We are presenting the old school flavour in our dish today
# 古法蒸武昌鱼
Old School Steamed Wuchang Fish
# 但是我们这方法要搁到其他菜系
But if we put this method in other cuisines
# 我们就是新方法
It would be regarded creative
# 借鉴其他菜系的一个特点是吧
That’s a characteristic of getting inspirations from another cuisine
# 再给它腌一下
Next, marinate the fish
# 盐 胡椒粉 葱姜 料酒
Salt, pepper, spring onions, ginger, and Chinese cooking wine
# 搓匀了
Massage the marinade evenly on the fish
# 没问题可以了 入了味
The fish should have absorbed all the favours by now
# 把盘儿拿过来
Pass me the plate
# 再给它切切
Cut the fish into smaller pieces
# 这样的在家合适 便于食用
It suits home cooking, and the fish will be easier to eat
# 摆成扇形的 这不就行了么
Present the fish in a fan shape. That’s nice
# 这不就孔雀开屏了么
It looks like a peacock spreading its tails
# 肥肉片 搁两片
Put on some fatty pork
# 借点肉片的香味儿
Which gives the fish some meaty aroma
# 待会葱姜给它挑出来
Discard the spring onions and ginger later
# 该调汁儿了吧咱们
We should start preparing the sauce
# 黄花 整齐点 够吗师父 够
Daylilies. Cut them neatly. Are these enough, Shifu? Yes
# 师弟这都弄好了是吧
Shidi, these are all done right?
# 里边都什么
What do we have in there?
# 枣 木耳 黄花
Red dates, black fungus, and daylilies
# 这个菜营养丰富
This dish is full of nutrition
# 而且跟这搭配的也好 荤素搭配
And it’s well-balanced with fish and veggies
# 要么说古法呢
That’s what we call ‘Old School’
# 然后咱调蚝油呗
Then, oyster sauce
# 蚝油有一勺
One tablespoon
# 再来一勺也行
Maybe another spoonful
# 胡椒粉 别太多了
Ground pepper. Not too much
# 搁点糖吧师父
Shall we add some sugar, Shifu?
# 糖来一点 来一点点 千万别多
Just a little bit. Never put too much sugar
# 糖提鲜的
Sugar is there to lift the umami
# 来点料酒
Some Chinese cooking wine
# 来点豉油 多来点没事
Some soy sauce. Generous amounts of it
# 粉子抓匀了它
Rub in some corn flour evenly
# 为什么加粉子
Why corn flour?
# 加完粉子以后 它那个汁就凝固了
The sauce will become viscous after adding it
# 再来点儿粉子
A bit more corn flour
# 来点葱油一拌 齐了
Mix in some spring onion oil. That’s it
# 真漂亮
How gorgeous!
# 放在上面让它铺开了 蒸蒸就行了
Spread them on the fish and they will be steamed at the same time
# 这时候你看 这葱油
Now look, more spring onion oil
# 为什么有的蒸完不润呢
Why are some fish not moist after steaming?
# 一个是亮
Firstly, it brightens the dish
# 第二个搁完这油还锁住水分 增香
Secondly, it seals the moisture in the fish, and increases the aroma
# 它还去腥
And it also removes the odour
# 准备好了 这就对了
All prepared. Wonderful
# 接下来就该蒸了吧
Now it’s time for steaming
# 现在闻着就香
It already smells so fragrant
# 那还用说
Of course
# 今天有师父跟梅哥给站脚助威
I have Shifu and Mei Ge to help and support me today
# 我心里更有底了
I’m much more confident
# 这道菜专门走宴会 接待外宾
This dish is exclusively served in State Banquets to welcome foreign guests
# 古法蒸排骨 古法蒸鸡都行
You can replace the fish with pork ribs or chicken if you want
# 因为它既保持了食材的新鲜味道
Because it not only keeps the fresh taste of the main ingredient
# 又借助了一些辅料的味道 都好吃
But also expresses the flavours from the minor ingredients, and they all taste great
# 锅开了咱们准备蒸
Water is boiling. Let’s steam the fish
# 必须得旺火蒸
You must use high heat
# 上锅喽
Into the pot
# 蒸完了再浇点油一呲 行了
Pour some sizzling oil on the fish after steaming. That sounds amazing
# 咱家里的火必须大火
We must use high heat when cooking at home
# 旺火速成十分钟
And it just takes 10 minutes
# 这边蒸着咱喝点水去 师父喝点水
While it’s steaming, let’s drink some water. Drink some water, Shifu
# 师父歇会儿
Take some rest, Shifu
# 好 时间到
Alright, time is up
# 非常漂亮
Exceptionally beautiful
# 这怎么看不见啊这个
Why can’t I see it?
# 这就行了
It should be fine now
# 扎一下看熟没熟 熟了
Stick the knife into the fish to check if it is cooked. Yes, it’s perfectly done
# 一道美味营养的
Take the delicious and nutritious
# 古法蒸武昌鱼 出锅了
Old School Steamed Wuchang Fish out of the pot
# 葱姜挑出去
Discard the spring onions and ginger
# 我来师父
Leave it to me, Shifu
# 这鱼还真漂亮 加上粉子还贼亮 真香嘿
This fish looks so lovely, and so shinny thanks to the corn flour. It’s so fragrant
# 葱油 这葱油好
The spring onion oil is fantastic
# 把汁给它倒一下
Discard the juice
# 底下那个（汁儿）就不要了
We don’t need the juice on the bottom there
# 待会呲点油 再淋点鱼汁
We will pour some sizzling oil and soy sauce in a minute
# 没问题 好 漂亮啊
Well done. Good job!
# 开下火准备呲油
Turn on the heat. Let’s prepare the sizzling oil
# 葱姜丝撒上
Put some juliennes of spring onions and ginger on the fish
# 来点胡椒粉
Some ground pepper
# 二合油 香油
Two types of oil are mixed together. Some sesame oil here
# 倒点香油
Add in some sesame oil
# 葱油加香油 古法武昌鱼
Spring onion oil plus sesame oil. Old School Steamed Wuchang Fish
# 温度得够啊 平地一声雷
The temperature must be high enough, so it sizzles loudly like the thunder
# 照中间呲
Pour in the centre of the dish
# 再给来点汁（豉油）
Add in some soy sauce
# 顺着边儿上 好喽
From the edge of the wok. Nicely done
# 再来点 满锅的烟火气
A bit more. A wokful of smoky flavour
# 顺着边上 你看这鱼汁的味儿这香
Pour the sauce around the fish. This soy sauce smells so aromatic
# 别弄鱼上 让它四周围
Don’t pour the sauce over the fish, instead, spread it around the fish
# 这个菜在之前 我跟小魏一块探讨
Before cooking this dish, I have been discussing it with Xiao Wei
# 就说一定要把这菜做成经典
We agree that we must make this dish a classic
# 因为武汉YQ马上就结束了
As the COVID-19 outbreak is about to end in Wuhan
# 我们要把这份爱献给武汉人民
We would like to share our love to the people in Wuhan
# 作为我们厨师
Being chefs like us
# 尽我们的所有的这份心思
We do our best and put all our care and love
# 全倾注到这份菜上了
Onto this dish
# 有木耳 有红枣 有黄花
We have black fungus, red dates, and daylilies
# 黄花又叫忘忧草
Daylilies are also called ‘Forgetting Sorrow’
# 吃完了以后心情愉悦
You will become much happier after eating them
# 我们战胜了YQ
We have defeated COVID-19
# 为武汉加油 为中国加油
Cheers for Wuhan, and cheers for China
# 这话说得太对了
You are absolutely right. Well spoken
# 感谢师傅 感谢梅师兄
Thanks to Shifu and Mei Ge
# 咱们开始尝尝吧
Let’s eat!
# 我在这闻 就这个香味扑鼻
I’m smelling the dish, and the fragrance is so mouth-watering
# 而且一下子想到了二十年前
And it reminds me of the time when I worked with Shifu at TLWC
# 跟师父在TLWC的时候
20 years ago
# 出这道菜
And we served this dish
# 那时候我还年轻呢是吧
I was still young at that time
# 这一晃六十多了
With a blink of eyes, I’m in my 60s now
# 这个菜我就不用评价
I don’t need to comment on this dish
# 能把二十多年前
Being able to pass on our love and thoughts
# 我们这份心思能够传承到现在
From 20 years ago till now
# 师父足矣
As your Shifu, I’m so satisfied
# 咱们要做菜就去用心做
We must cook with our heart
# 搁到今天 今天我可以这么说
Even today, I can still confidently say
# 这道菜 依然不落后
That this dish is never out of fashion
# 所以说我希望你用心
So, I hope you cook with your heart
# 把这份情感的东西给传承下去
And pass this passion and emotion onto the next generation
# 比什么都重要
This is more important than anything else
# 咱们一块鱼 再蘸点汁
Pick up one piece of fish, and dip it in the sauce
# 还得蘸点黄花木耳吃
Eat it with some daylilies and black fungus
# 真好
So yummy
# 又鲜 又滑 又有回味
It’s umami, moist, and has a brilliant aftertaste
# 武汉好久不见
Wuhan, long time no see
# 中国加油
Cheers for China
# 黄花木耳蒸的比这鱼还好吃
The steamed daylilies and black fungus are even tastier than the fish